our bodies are meant to have a certain
balance of sodium and potassium intake
yet the majority of people in the u.s
get vastly more than the recommended
amount of sodium and it turns out far
less than the recommended amount of
potassium
in this three-part video series we'll
look at the optimal levels of sodium
potassium and then add a salt substitute
that may help balance out this ratio and
save lives
[Music]
worldwide physical inactivity accounted
for more than 10 million years of
healthy life lost but what we eat
accounts for nearly 20 times that
unhealthy diets shave hundreds of
millions of disability-free years off of
people's lives every year
what are the worst aspects of our diets
four out of the five the deadliest
dietary traps involve not eating enough
of certain foods not eating enough whole
grains not eating enough fruits not
eating enough nuts and seeds and not
eating enough vegetables but our most
fatal flaw
is too much salt that's on the order of
15 times deadlier than diets too high in
soda for example just to keep things in
perspective
there remains no single more effective
public health action related to
nutrition than the reduction of sodium
in the diet
this is why national and international
health organizations have called for
warning labels on salt packets and salt
shakers with messages like you know too
much sodium in the diet causes high
blood pressure and increases risk of
stomach cancer stroke heart disease and
kidney disease limit your use
salt also increases inflammation
for example sodium intake is associated
with increased disease activity and
multiple sclerosis an inflammatory
autoimmune nerve condition
about three to four times the
exacerbation rate in those with medium
or high sodium intakes compared to those
getting less than a teaspoon of salt
total in a day
just so you can see higher sodium levels
in the tissues of those who suffer from
lupus and other serous inflammatory
autoimmune disease you can correlate
high sodium levels in the spinal cord of
ms patients with the disease and
decreased structural integrity
where's sodium found though
really crappy food so it's hard to know
if increased salt intake is just a
marker for a bad diet overall
but what we do know is that salt and
high blood pressure are cause and effect
how because we have more than a hundred
randomized controlled trials
demonstrating that if you cut down an
added salt your blood pressure is full
and the more you cut down the better
part of the mechanism may actually be
the damage salt may do to your
microbiome the the friendly flora in
your gut
and no wonder our bodies evolved only to
handle about 750 milligrams a day the
american heart association says we
should stay under at least twice that
about but
we're eating more than four times what's
natural and it's only getting worse
increasing over the last decade anyone
care to guess what percentage of
americans exceed the 1 500 milligram
upper limit recommendation
98.8
and that was more than a decade ago
the vast majority of u.s adults consume
too much sodium and at the same time too
little potassium a mineral that lowers
blood pressure less than 2 percent of
u.s adults consume the recommended daily
minimum intake of potassium so more than
98 of americans eat potassium deficient
diets
this deficiency is even more striking
when comparing our current intake with
that of our ancestors who consumed large
amounts of dietary potassium we evolved
getting probably more than 10 000
milligrams a day
the recommendation is to get around at
least half that yet most of us don't
even come anywhere close
put the two guidelines together and
sodium and potassium golds are currently
met by less than
0.015 percent of the us population so
we're talking close to 99.99
non-compliance as in only one in 6 000
americans even hits the recommended
guidelines
what about using potassium-based salt
substitutes instead of using sodium
chloride salt why not shake on some
potassium chloride
seems a little too good to be true i
mean same salty taste but you're
reducing sodium while at the same time
increasing your potassium intake is
there a catch
are potassium-based salt substitutes
safe effective we'll find out
next
[Music]
you